<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Physicke for body and soule Shevving that the maladies of the one, proceede from the sinnes of the other: with a remedie against both, prescribed by our heauenly physitian Iesus Christ. Deliuered in a sermon at Buckden in Huntingtonsh, before the right reuerend Father in God the Lord Bishop of Lincolne then being, by E. Heron Bachelor of Diuinitie, and sometime fellow of Trin. Colledge in Cambridge.</title>
            <author>Heron, Edward, d. 1650.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03099</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13227</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115187</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850406</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850406</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15607</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03099)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15607)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1274:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Physicke for body and soule Shevving that the maladies of the one, proceede from the sinnes of the other: with a remedie against both, prescribed by our heauenly physitian Iesus Christ. Deliuered in a sermon at Buckden in Huntingtonsh, before the right reuerend Father in God the Lord Bishop of Lincolne then being, by E. Heron Bachelor of Diuinitie, and sometime fellow of Trin. Colledge in Cambridge.</title>
                  <author>Heron, Edward, d. 1650.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 47, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Legatt for Francis Constable, and are to be sold at his shoppe in Paules Church-yard at the signe of the White Lyon,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Emmanuel College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15607:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15607:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>PHYSICKE FOR BODY AND SOVLE.</p>
            <p>SHEVVING THAT THE MALADIES OF THE one, proceede from the ſinnes of the other: with a remedie againſt both, preſcribed by our heauenly Phyſitian IESVS CHRIST.</p>
            <p>DELIVERED IN A SERMON AT <hi>BVCKDEN</hi> IN <hi>HVNTINGTONSH,</hi> before the Right Reuerend Father in God the Lord Biſhop of <hi>Lincolne</hi> then being, by <hi>E. Heron</hi> Bachelor of Diuinitie, and ſometime fellow of Trin. Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Vtteipſum ſerues, non expergiſceris?—</q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Iohn Legatt</hi> for <hi>Francis Conſtable,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shoppe in <hi>Paules</hi> Church-yard at the Signe of the White Lyon. 1621.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15607:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15607:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE AND Right Reuerend Father in God, IOHN Lord Biſhop of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> Lord Keeper of the Great Seale of <hi>England,</hi> one of his Maieſties moſt Sacred Councell the increaſe of temporall, and complement of glorie eternall.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the generall concourſe of thoſe who runne to doe your Lordſhippe honour, I, (who haue taſted as freely of your former fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours as the moſt of them) could no longer containe, but
<pb facs="tcp:15607:3"/> with Ahimaaz muſt runne alſo, though without a full er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raund; perſwading my ſelfe that the ſwift wings of ſincere affection would carry me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the formoſt <hi>Cuſhi.</hi> Pleaſeth it therfore your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to accept this firſt argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my vowed duty, vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſometime at one of your places of reſidency, graced by the audience of one of your predeceſſors, but now preſt for your Lordſhips ſeruice. It can adde nothing to the magnitude of your honour, no more then a
<pb facs="tcp:15607:3"/> droppe to the Ocean, but by your Lordſhips acceptance it may increaſe the honouring multitude by One. The Lord of Lords who hath begun this great worke in you, perfect the ſame to the glory of himſelfe, the aduancement of his Church and diſreſpected Churchmen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Euer at your Honours ſeruice in the Lord, E. Heron.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:15607:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15607:4"/>
            <head>PHYSICKE FOR Body and Soule.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Ioh. 5. part of the 14. verſ.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Behold thou art made whole: ſinne no more, leaſt a worſe thing happen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E that promiſed to make his Apoſtles Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhers of men, <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.19. Vſed A two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold nette wherewith to catch and drawe men vnto him ſayes S. <hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Chryſoſt. in <hi>22,</hi> Luc.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </item>
               </list> the net of wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders, and of words. By the firſt Hee caught thoſe many who beleeued in his name, when they ſaw the miracles
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15607:5"/> which He did. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.23. <hi>(b)</hi> By the ſecond He encloſed his very enemies, thoſe Officers who were ſent to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend and bring him before the High Prieſts and Phariſees. They were ſo entangled in the net of his heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doctrine, that they had no power to lay violent hands vpon him, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned with this anſwer, neuer man ſpake as that man did. <note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 7 46.</note> Our bleſſed Sauiour vſeth both theſe nets in the recouering of a certaine poore, lame, and diſeaſed man, the ſubiect of this Text. Firſt He heales him with the the bare word of his mouth, <hi>Surge &amp; tolle grabatum,</hi> verſe 8. Him who by ordinarie meanes could not be healed in 38. yeares before, verſe 5. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly He leaues him not here, but that He might be wholly taken as well in ſoule as body He caſts vpon him the net of his words and doctrine. Behold thou that wert thus many years ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for thy ſinnes, art now through
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15607:5"/> mercy reſtored to thy perfect health, take heede leaſt falling into the ſame ſinnes againe thou pull downe Gods iudgements after a more fearefull manner: where our bleſſed Sauiour puts him in minde of his long deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red recouerie, ſhewes him the cauſe of his miſerie, and giues him an item, to preuent a worſer calamity. <hi>Behold thou art made whole, &amp;c.</hi> Out of which words, without vexing them either with curioſitie or multiplicitie of diuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ariſe naturally theſe 3. parts
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoratio be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficij. Beholde thou arte made whole</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitio, officij. Sinne no more</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatio ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicij. Leaſt a worſe thing come vnto thee.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The commemorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the benefite containes the Manner and Matter: <hi>Behold,</hi> The manner: <hi>Thou art made whole:</hi> The matter. To begin with the firſt.</p>
            <p>This demonſtratiue <hi>Ecce,</hi> Is not a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15607:6"/> note of approbation in the Receiuer of the benefit, as if through his long patience He had merited this fauour at Chriſts hand, being ſet out vnto vs as a grieuous ſinner:<note place="margin">Iam. 1.5.</note> Nor a ſigne of exprobation in the Giuer, For God giueth freely and vpbraideth no man with his gifts: Nor a vaine repetiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of oſtentation in our Sauiour, for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it would haue run in the firſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,<note place="margin">Theophraſt. in charact. ſuperbi.</note> 
               <hi>Ecce ſanum te feci,</hi> as it is noted in the character of the proud man. But it is a note of Remembrance &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration vttered to this end, that the benefit of God ſo plentifully beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon him ſhould not now be writ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten in the duſt to be blown away with the ſlight blaſt of forgetfulneſſe, but remaine fixed, and ſetled in his heart written as the Prophet ſpeakes with a pen of yron, and the point of a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond to continue for euer: And with good reaſon, for the very Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then could taxe the whole kinde for want of this vertue, comparing man
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15607:6"/> in this regard <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Epigra. Anthol.</note> to a bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe veſſel that tranſmits what euer is put into the ſame. A ſinne begotten in our firſt parents and propagated in their poſterity. Take a taſt of it in the Iſraelites, Gods moſt obliged people, who had ſuch ſenſible feelings of his fauor as they might be iuſtly tearmed by the Philoſophers word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened with his benefits:<note place="margin">Ariſtotle Ethic. Seneca de benef.</note> yet with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it fared, as with thoſe of whom <hi>Senec. Apud quos non diutius in animo donata quam in vſu.</hi> Witneſſe that God rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked the red ſea, and it was dried, led them in the deepe as in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, cauſing the waters to couer their oppreſſors, &amp;c. Then beleeued they his words &amp; laud praiſes to his name, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.12. But incontinently they forgat his workes and would not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waite his counſell. <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore leaſt we ſhould <hi>deglutire benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia Dei</hi> ſwallow down the benefits of God without ruminating on them
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15607:7"/> by due meditation: or leaſt we might impute them to our owne deſerts, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificing to our own nets and kiſsing our owne hands as the Prophet hath it for catching and procuring the ſame, our bleſſed Sauiour ſtirres vp this reſtored man, and in him all that enioy the like benefit to taſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how good the Lord hath beene vnto vs. <hi>Behold.</hi> The matter fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes. <hi>Thou art made whole.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The benefite of health may chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge all poſsible thankes at any mans hand—<hi>Vt corpus redimas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ovid.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> skinne for skinne and all that a man hath will He giue for his life, was the laſt and the beſt argument the Diuell could vſe to infringe <hi>Iobs</hi> faith and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence:<note place="margin">Iob. 2.5.</note> 
               <hi>Stretch out now thine hand vpon him and ſee if He will not blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme thee to thy face.</hi> But health is the life of life,<note place="margin">Senee.</note> Since <hi>non viuere ſed valere vita eſt,</hi> life without health is but a lingring death: and therefore
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15607:7"/> the Prophet makes it a great part of his happie man <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to bee ſound of winde and limbe,<note place="margin">Thales ap. Diog Laect.</note> for — <hi>Si capiti bene, &amp;c.</hi> If it be well with vs in the whole ſtructure of our body can princely riches adde more, yea they cannot yeeld ſo much happineſſe of themſelues, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Plutarch <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Neither can the glorious Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme of a King aſſwage one whit the ach of his head, nor the pretious ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net command the leaſt diſeaſe from the finger. Yet howſoeuer the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of health be great in it ſelfe, it was here greater if we review the former condition of him one whom it was conferred. Wheras <hi>Seneca</hi> makes but three things grieuous in euery diſeaſe which are either <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Dolor Corporis.</hi> Affliction of body.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Intermiſsio vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptatis.</hi> Intermiſsion of all ioy and pleaſure.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Timor mortis.</hi> Feare of death.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Beſide theſe this diſeaſed patient was ouercome.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:15607:8"/>1. Of pouertie, as great a diſeaſe as the former,<note place="margin">Menander.</note> — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, no burden more burdenſome then pouertie, inſomuch as <hi>Hecuba</hi> beeing brought to that extremitie calles her misfortunes;<note place="margin">Euryp. in Hecubae.</note> — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. ſuch as ſurpaſſed the ſufferance of nature: being numbred among the curſes of the Law,<note place="margin">Deut. 28.22.</note> yea accounted ſo great a curſe with the Heathen that <hi>Plutarch</hi> reportes many to auoyde the ſame, haue beene content to throw them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues headlong from high rockes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſea preuenting that miſerie of life by a ſudden and certaine death. Now of this diſeaſe laboured this poore creeple who wanted meanes to procure a man to put him into the poole when the water was troubled.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He was accompanied no doubt with pouerties neceſſarie attendant Contempt,<note place="margin">Iuvenal.</note> —<hi>Nil habet infaelix pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtas, &amp;c.</hi> The poore man is deſpiſed of his neighbour, ſayes the wiſeſt of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15607:8"/> men. The Iewes according to their receiued opinion,<note place="margin">Ethniorum opinio miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros eſſe. Diis inviſos heni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius in Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crit.</note> accounting him Gods enemy becauſe of his great mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, as they did thoſe Galileans whoſe blood <hi>Pilate</hi> mingled with their own ſacrifice (for refuſing to offer for the the health of <hi>Caeſar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theophylact in <hi>13.</hi> Luc.</note> as <hi>Theophylact</hi> notes it.) They cared not to reach vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him their helping hand of pity.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The long continuance in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity, made it the more incurable in it ſelfe, and the more inſufferable to the patient beeing of no leſſe then thirty eight yeares regiment, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it had gathered together ſuch a multitude of ill-affected humours, as they not onely ſurpriſed the whole body, out were able to oppoſe the ſtrongeſt art of the moſt expert Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian, ſince <hi>Sero madicina, &amp;c.</hi> Inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate Diſeaſes which haue placed their garriſons in our mortall taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles cannot be diſplaced by ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry meanes.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:15607:9"/>4. Such a grieuous diſeaſe of the body could not but cauſe as grieuous diſeaſes in the minde by reaſon of that Sympathie or compaſſion betweene theſe two yoake-fellowes: the firſt whereof is a longing expectation of the bodies eaſe and her quiet from the troubled water,<note place="margin">Tertul. de bapt<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Seall. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> dorp.</note> for <hi>Quatannis id fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum,</hi> and it cured all manner diſeaſes whatſoeuer, verſ. 4. Now <hi>Carnifices a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>mi mora &amp; expectatio.</hi> Expectation is as the hangman of the minde tortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſame betweene the two gives of hope and deſpaire, Hee well ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped that after the many nights of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, the mourning of ioy now appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched wherein he ſhould be reſtored to his perfect ſtrength, but his expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was wholy fruſtrated, his hope was with ſo many deceiuings quite ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that it became hopeleſſe, which brought one his ſoule the laſt of all her diſeaſes, a finall deſpaire of enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that miraculous benefite of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15607:9"/> for he concludes with our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, that he was alwaies preuented by others who ſtepped in before him, as it is in the ſeauenth verſe of this chap. Recollect wee then the greatneſſe of this benefit beſtowed on him. Beſides that his body is no more afflicted, his ioy &amp; pleaſure no longer intermitted, and the feare of death ouerpaſſed, his pouertie is hereby releeued, his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt ſalued, the long continuance in his diſeaſe ended, his racking expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion fully ſatisfied, and his finall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpayre finally preuented. <hi>Beholde thou art made whole.</hi> Wherein the bounty of our bleſſed Sauiour is yet further extended to him, who in this our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample ſhewes ſufficiently that hee is the only true Phyſitian of mans ſoule, in that hee makes this mans bodily cure but a preparatiue to the cure of his ſicke ſoule,<note place="margin">Ang. in lec.</note> 
               <hi>Fecit quod videri pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, vt ſavatetur quod videri non poee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat.</hi> He makes a cure vpon that which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15607:10"/> was obvious to the eye of man, the body that ſo hee might make way for the inuiſible cure of the minde,<note place="margin">Dat viuendi morem, dat innocentiae legem poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulit ſanita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem. Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</note> and therefore in the next place he ſhewes him the cauſe of his miſerie which was ſinne, for his humiliation, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhes him to ſinne no more for preuention of a worſe euill, and that is the ſecond part vnder our conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. Viz.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. part,</note>The commonition, <hi>Sinne no more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He had ſinned or elſe he had neuer beene afflicted, for <hi>Paena non praecedit culpa.</hi> Puniſhment neuer goes before, but dogges ſinne at the heeles: wherin he had ſinned is onely knowne to him that knowes only the diuers windings of mans heart. To thinke with ſome in Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> that his ſin was the manifeſting of Chriſt his Phyſitian to the Iewes, as a tranſgreſſor of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, beſides that the lettar is oppoſite to that conceit, it incurs the ſoloeciſme of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, For this ſinne (if there had
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15607:10"/> beene any ſuch) muſt needs bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted after, it could not be before his healing: <hi>Et fi accuſandi gratia dixſsit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſtome in locum.</note> ſayes <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> hauing relation to the 15. verſe, <hi>Timuiſſet vtique peiora, cum minantis poteſtatem eſſet expertus.</hi> We rather ioyne with the Apoſtle, <hi>In multis impingimus omnes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 32.</note> All of vs of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend in many things; Theſe many things then at the obiect of this admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition: Looke therefore how diuers ſinne is, but ſinne is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Peccare eſt tanquam linias tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, Cic. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rad.</note> like the continued quantity admittes infinite ſections and diuiſions, euen ſo extenſiue is this admonition applied to vs, prohibiting all manner of ſinne incident to the nature of man. I will confine the infinitenes therof to theſe termes.</p>
            <p>Either <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Quod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Quantulum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cunque</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Quale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt, whether it bee a ſinne
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15607:11"/> againſt the firſt or ſecond table, <hi>Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatio legis eſt copulatiua;</hi> Holines and righteouſneſſe are ioyned together in the Benedict, holineſſe towards God, and righteouſnes towards our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, according to the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 4. <hi>Vlt.</hi>
               </note> that he which lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth God ſhould loue his brother al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo: ſo that an Indulgence cannot ſalue vp the breach of any part of the morall law which is perpetuall, nor a diſpenſation from any mortall man giue liberty to the leaſt ſinne which is againſt the ſame. And the reaſon is for that the diſpenſation againſt the lawe muſt be graunted by as great authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as the lawe was firſt made, but the morall lawe grounded on the lawe of nature, was founded by the author, &amp; creatour of nature God himſelfe, and therfore by him only may it be diſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed withall, which the ſchoolemen acknowledge in that theologicall axiome,<note place="margin">Altified.</note> 
               <hi>Praeſcripta legis naturalis non
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15607:11"/> ſunt diſpenſabilia:</hi> But the morall law of God what is it but the law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture written in tables of ſtone.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Quantulumcunque,</hi> Not onely thoſe monſtrous ſinnes of the olde world, or thoſe crying ſinnes of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Gomorrha, Niniuie, which were ſo bold and impudent as to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance themſelues before the face of Almighty God,<note place="margin">Neſcio non poſſumus le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue aliquod precatum dicere quod in Dei con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templum admittitur. Hieronym. Ep. <hi>14.</hi> Auguſt. Ep. <hi>108.</hi>
               </note> but euen ſmall ſinnes as wee eſteeme them, for the ſmall egge of the Cockatrice will in time prooue a deuouring ſerpent, and if the little theeues get once in at the windowes, they will ſoone ſet open the doores for the great ones to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and deſpoyle vs, <hi>Quid intereſt</hi> (ſayes S. <hi>Augustine</hi>) <hi>vtrum vuo gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di fluctu nauis obruatur, &amp;c.</hi> what skils it whether the ſhipſuffer wracke from one huge billow that ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmes her, or by ſome few ſmall leakes which in time ſinke her, ſeeing the wages of this little as that great
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15607:12"/> ſinne in its owne nature is eternall death.<note place="margin">Rom. 6.23</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Qualecunque,</hi> of what nature, quality, or condition ſoeuer the ſin be. As firſt, whether they be ſinnes of age or ſinnes of youth, <hi>Detur aliquid aetati</hi> was but a heathen mans diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Chriſt ſhed his warmeſt blood for them, and requires that they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue al others ſhould not ſpare their beſt yeares in his quarrell, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> writes to the young man eſpecially becauſe they are ſtrong and able to beare the burden of the day,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 1.</note> yea <hi>Contra aſsiduum An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochum generoſe pugnet emnis aetas,</hi> As it is rendred out of <hi>Nazian.</hi> For ſuch is Gods husbandry as no ſeaſon prooues vnſeaſonable for ſowing the ſeedes of piety, ſow thy ſeeds in the morning and in the euening let not thy hand reſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether ſinnes iſſuing from the temperature of mans body. If
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15607:12"/> the cholerick were priuiledged from the praedominancie of that humour to caſt forth his ſudden flaſhes of wrath and reuenge,<note place="margin">Gen. 4.23.</note> 
               <hi>Lamec</hi> might iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the killing a man in his wound and a yong man in his hurt. If the ſanguine might beguile the time in dalliance, in chambering and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe: S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> had ſpent his oyle vainely in <hi>Dauids</hi> Apologie.<note place="margin">Dictum de Vacia igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vo civc. Vacia hic ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt. Sen. Ep. <hi>Prou. 10.</hi>
               </note> If the flegmatique might bury himſelfe quicke in the graue of idleneſſe, He neede not put it of, By a Lyon in the way, a Lyon in the ſtreete. If the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholicke might harbour darke and diſmall thoughts and bring forth deſperate effects, diſcontented <hi>Achi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophel</hi> might make a long letter of himſelfe without praeiudice to the letter of Gods Law. But nature muſt bee ſubdued by grace, It beeing the firſt ſtep into Chriſtianitie to denie our ſelues, and yeeld all ſubiection to the will of God.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:15607:13"/>3. Whether they bee ſinnes of conformitie,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.2. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> As to pride it with the Spaniard, to drinke drunke with the Dutch, to be light of promiſe with the Carthaginian, to play the lyer with the Cretenſian, or the lying Aequiuocator with the Ieſuited Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane;<note place="margin">
                  <p>Punica fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Prouerb.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> For the time was when <hi>Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> would rather returne to Carthage vpon his faith giuen though to the moſt exquiſite torments then to haue ſlipped away by a mentall eluſion. Wee are taught in Gods Schoole though Iſrael play the harlot, yet Iudah ſhould not ſinne; Thus wee reade of the riuer Alphaeus that it conuaies it ſelfe through the Sea breaking forth to his beloued Are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſa,<note place="margin">Lucian dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log.</note> and yet participates no whit with the ſeaes brackiſh humor; Thus <hi>Lot</hi> was found chaſte in the midſt of Sodom, <hi>Iob</hi> truly religious in the ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous land of Vz, and many Saints in <hi>Caeſar Neroes</hi> houſhold.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:15607:13"/>
            <p>Laſtly, whether they be ſins pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from a good intenſion, euen that makes not ſimply a good action; for <hi>Bonum eſt de integra cauſa</hi> ſayes <hi>Aquinas:</hi> both beginning, meanes, and end muſt bee right, or elſe the whole action will prooue wrong, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the leaſt leauen of euill ſowres the whole lumpe of goodneſſe; Take it in <hi>Vzzahs</hi> ſtaying the Arke ready to fall, it was well meant as Hee thought and intended to a good end: yet foraſmuch as He did it neither <hi>authoritatiue,</hi> being no Prieſt,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 6.</note> nor <hi>ex mandato ſpeciali,</hi> by any ſpeciall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand or ſecret inſinuation of Gods Spirit moouing him thereto, but his owne appetiue will, God ſlew him in the ſame place. Here then,<note place="margin">Fines &amp; que ſunt ad finem debent eſſe eiuſdem generis.</note> 
               <hi>In ordine ad bonum ſpirituale</hi> for the Popes power in temporals ouer the Lords Annointed to vpholde the Arke of Gods ſeruice will prooue but <hi>ordo inordinatus,</hi> being neither primatiue in himſelfe, nor deriuatiue from the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15607:14"/> true fountaine of all power. The firſt is wiſedomes peculiar, <hi>Per me Reges regnant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 8.15.</note> and it is the Lord that put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth downe the mightie from their ſeate: and therefore <hi>Super aſpidem &amp; baſitiſcum</hi> was as violently rent from Chriſt by Pope <hi>Alexander,</hi> as iniuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly put vpon the ſacred neck of the Emperour by the foote of more then <hi>Luciferian</hi> pride. For the ſecond Chriſt himſelfe had it not <hi>qua homo, Regnum meum non eſt de hoc mundo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Delegatus nihil facit authoritate propaeia Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>normitan.</note> my kingdome is not of this world, how then can the Pope Vicar that which was neuer committed or tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto him: It remaines, that this indirect intenſion proues a direct vſurpation. And here likewiſe falles their opinion who are ſo far from vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding as they bend all their intenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the pulling down of the Arke of Gods ſeruice in regard of decent orders, comely rites, beutiful ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, &amp;c. Let vs begin with the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine from whence theſe vnhallowed
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15607:14"/> intenſions haue their origination, we ſhall finde that to bee an Erroneous conſcience ſpurred on by vnaduiſed zeale, I cal it erroneous <hi>quia co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcientia nunquam obligat in virtute propria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aquinas.</note> 
               <hi>ſed in virtute praecepti diuini,</hi> it binds not by vertue of its own direction, but in the vertue &amp; ſtrength of Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, but Gods commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is, that all things be done de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently and in order, and that euery ſoule bee ſubiect to the higher pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in things not oppoſite to the high eſt power,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.5. The very Geneua note in 5. Act. 36. Is, that in matters which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion wee muſt not attempt any thing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der colour of zeale be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide our vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note> not ſo much for feare as for conſcience ſake, For in ſuch things <hi>plus obligat praeceptum prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipis &amp; praelati quam propria conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> (ſaies <hi>Hales</hi>) Our conſcience in ſuch caſes muſt bee captiuated to lawfull authoritie. And therefore the ſtreame of ſuch intenſions muſt beginne at this true fountaine, and not iſſue out of the broken pits of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery mechanicall phanſie and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:15607:15"/>
            <p>Secondly, for the meane furthering this intentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Thats no leſſe (ſay they) then the Scripture, but the Scripture is the Canon by which all our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhould bee ſquared:<note place="margin">Ariſt. Rhet. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Yet as the Philoſoper ſaid of a law politicall though it bee in it ſelfe moſt perfect &amp; ſtreight, the Iudge by his wreſting interpretation might make it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> peruerſe and crooked: ſo may we ſay of Gods law, eſpecially if vnlettered folke haue the interpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therof in their hand, to the which is required the greateſt art and ſcience. If any ſay the text is plaine, the letter apparent, S. <hi>Nazian.</hi> anſwers that <hi>Studium lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terae est pallium iniquitatis,</hi> the ſticking too much to the letter in generall is the cloake of much impietie,<note place="margin">Sic. Chili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtae ex <hi>Apoc. 20.2</hi>
               </note> Did not <hi>Arrius</hi> fall into his haereſie by hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding himſelfe to the letter, <hi>Pater ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior me. Ioh.</hi> 4. Did not the Donatiſts goe about to prooue theirs to be the only true Church by the letter of the text. <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Tell mee where thou
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15607:15"/> feedeſt and where thou lyeſt at noone, Vti cubas in meridie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Alphonſus de Caſtro in verbo Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia.</note> They would prooue from hence <hi>Eccleſiam ad ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam meridionalem plagam quam ipſi incolebant redactam,</hi> that the True Church was only to bee found in thoſe Southerne parts which they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited, but it fared with them as it did with thoſe of whom <hi>Salomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 30. <hi>vlt.</hi>
               </note> They that wring their noſe fetch out blood, which S. <hi>Gregorie</hi> interprets, That they who wring, wreſt, or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interpret Scripture (a thing incident to vnlearned people as appeares in the 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16.) they bring forth <hi>aut haereſim aut phreneſim,</hi> either an haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie or a phrenſie. And therefore the H. Ghoſt giues an item to ſuch daring Prophets. <hi>The time ſhal come that they ſhall be aſhamed of their viſions,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 13.5</note> 
               <hi>&amp; ſhall ſay I am no Prophet, I am an husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, man taught me to be an heard man from my youth vp.</hi> So that this <hi>medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> cannot bee a rule to them who haue not true and vniuerſall know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15607:16"/> to vſe the ſame.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, for the End terminating, what is their ſcope but Innouation A monſter in a well eſtabliſhed Church breeding more euils then euer did the lake Lerna.<note place="margin">Vincent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rra haereſ.</note> In matters of doctrine <hi>noue non noua,</hi> wee may handle the point after a new manner ſo that wee inferre no new and exorbitant mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; but in matter of Church order <hi>nec noue nec noua,</hi> neither noueltie of manner nor of matter ought to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced,<note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> ſince <hi>ipſa mutatio conſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinis, &amp;c.</hi> the change of an ancient cuſtome in the Church, if it ſhould ſomewhat helpe by the vtility, it would hurt as much, or more by the noueltie, and therefore <hi>primo diuinae legis authoritate, &amp;c.</hi> ſayes <hi>Vincent.</hi> Firſt the Word of God written muſt guide, but where that is ſilent, <hi>Tunc eccleſiea Catholicae traditio,</hi> Then the inſtitution &amp; tradition of the Church muſt take place, Hence is it that the holy Ghoſt bids vs not to remooue
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15607:16"/> the auncient bounds which our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers haue ſet,<note place="margin">Pro. 22.28.</note> teaching by this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legory not to bring innouations into the Church contrary to what wee haue receiued from godly antiquity, and theres a curſe annexed to ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouators. He that breaks downe the hedge, him ſhall a ſerpent bite,<note place="margin">Eccl. 10.8.</note> the hedge of godly order as well in Church as common-wealth, as <hi>Liri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſis</hi> expounds it, him ſhall Satan the ſubtile ſerpent bite. This was the caſe of <hi>Donatus,</hi> firſt hee breakes downe the hedge by innouation, then the ſerpent bites and ſtings him on forward to fall into open ſciſme with <hi>Caecilianus</hi> the godly Biſhop of Carthage &amp; his orthodoxal Church,<note place="margin">Alphonſus de Laiſtio.</note> 
               <hi>Poſtea ſciſma in haereſim commutauit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In the Swinckſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians, the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts, Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts.</note> He turned ſciſme into plaine haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and then this gangrene ſpreads it ſelfe ſo farre, as the contagion ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hath reached euen to our times. This may be the cauſe why S. <hi>Paul</hi> does earneſtly wiſh,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.12.</note> that they were cut off who did diſturb the Galatians
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15607:17"/> foreſeeing that by the Schiſmes and diſſentions the ſeameleſſe coate of Chriſt the Embleme of his Church (as S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> hath it) might by theſe meanes bee rent and torne aſunder.<note place="margin">Cyprian de Vast. Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae.</note> Theſe intenſions therefore cannot attaine their wiſhed end, but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſaying of <hi>Gamaliel</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they haue proceeded from man and not from God they haue neuer taken place but receiued <hi>Vzzahs</hi> doome <hi>Perez-Vzzah</hi> to bee diuided and ſcattered euen from our late Queenes regiment vnto this preſent time and therfore let ſuch <hi>Innouators</hi> apprehend this admonition:<note place="margin">2. Sam. 6.8.</note>
               <note place="margin">Act. 5.38.</note> 
               <hi>Sinne no more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if no more, then our ſpirituall reſurrection from the graue of ſinne muſt be ſpeedie and conſtant, ſpeedy euen from the preſent period of time conſtant, to the laſt point of life; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>non amplius,</hi> No more imploies both. For the firſt, that it ought to be without delation the bodily, Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15607:17"/> teaches that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Hypocrat. aphoriſ. <hi>9.</hi> lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> the infected parts of the body, the more they are cheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, the more they are endamaged: ſo fares it with a ſoule habituated in ſinne by a frequent cuſtome in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the conſcience becomes ſo ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and the heart ſo hardned as they will not receiue the ſoft impreſſion of Gods ſpirit,<note place="margin">Conſuetudo altera natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra.</note> it proouing as eaſie to recouer a dead man in body as a ſicke man in ſoule who is growne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to yeares of ſinne, and ſo goes on from darknes to darknes vntill hee come to the vtter darkeneſſe where he findes no other comfort, but wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, wailing and gnaſhing of teeth. And as it muſt bee ſpeedy, ſo muſt it be conſtant, for <hi>Non initia Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum ſed fines coronantur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern.</note> becauſe one may begin in the ſpirit but end in the fleſh,<note place="margin">Ariſt. eth.</note> and therfore as in the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lympicke games not the faireſt nor the ſtrongeſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c, but of thoſe which ſtriued, they that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15607:18"/> continued to the end won and wore the garland: ſo in the Chriſtian war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare againſt our ghoſtly enemies, ſin, hell, Satan, if wee continue faithfull vnto the death, God will giue vs the crowne of life. <hi>Sinne no more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 2.10.</note>The admonition is both iuſt, and neceſſarie. Iuſt for wee are for the moſt part no ſooner confirmed in health and ſtrength but we are ready to ſummon vp our forces,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Nazian <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and giue vp our members as weapons of vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe to ſinne, as ſouldiers doe yeeld themſelues to their captaines to warre vnder their banner: Thus the Iſraelites when they waxed fat, and in good liking ſpurned with their heele,<note place="margin">Deut. 32.i5</note> therefore they forſooke God that made them and regarded not the ſtrong God of their ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: To ſuch the ſaying of <hi>Seneca</hi> might fitly be applyed <hi>Tutius aegro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſſent</hi> when they turne this gift of God into wantonneſſe and abuſe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15607:18"/> their ſtrength to the powring in of much wine and bearing ſtrong drink. And neceſſary,<note place="margin">i Tim. 5.6,</note> for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the life of ſinne is the death of the ſoule, and therefore the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow that gaue her ſelfe ouer to luſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full pleaſures <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, her liuing bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy was but the ſepulcher of her dead ſoule,<note place="margin">Bern. med.</note> But how ſhall wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man—<hi>Cuius conceptio culpa eſt.</hi> Who euen in his conception is war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in vncleane blood through o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall contagion,<note place="margin">Auguſtine.</note> and ſtayes not there but in a ſhort progreſſe of time does <hi>ponere Adam ſuper A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> by his actuall tranſgreſſions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more lame in his ſoule, then this lame man was erewhile in his body bee capable of Chriſts admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition? Can a badde tree bring forth good fruite? Doe men gather grapes from thornes, or figges from thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles? I anſwer.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue a ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t deſire not to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15607:19"/> ſinne, as the prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid, <hi>Oh that I were ſo vpright that I might keepe thy commaundements and as the Hart brayeth after the water brooks,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 42.1.</note> 
               <hi>ſo panteth my ſoule after thee oh Lord, Magna pars bonitatis velle fieri bonum,</hi> it is a great ſtep vnto goodnes to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be good.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act. 24.16.</hi> ſc. pro Statu viatorum.</note>2. If he haue a conſtant endeauor not to ſinne, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> had who endeauoured alwayes to keepe a cleare conſcience both before God and man, and as <hi>Zachary</hi> &amp; <hi>Elizabeth</hi> are ſaide to walke in all the ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and commaundements of the Lord without reproofe.<note place="margin">Luc. 1.6.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. If when he ſinnes he does it not with a full force but with a relucta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion—<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Homer. Il. <hi>Rom. 7.19.</hi>
               </note> doing euill, but the euill hee would not doe—<hi>Cum trahit invitum nova vis.</hi> Then God accepts the will for the deede, then is he pronounced bleſſed, becauſe his wickednes is forgiuen and his ſinne is couered in which ſence Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15607:19"/> Tum tota lex impletur, quando quicquid non fit, ignoſcitur.</hi> So from ſinne I am led to the puniſhment of it, to terrifie vs from medling with the pleaſing baytes thereof, which is the third generall part. Viz.</p>
            <p>The commination,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3. Part.</hi> Herodot,</note> 
               <hi>Leaſt a worſe thing happen vnto thee.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Great ſinnes deſerue great puniſhments. The ſinne of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidiuation was thought ſo great that the Nouatians would yeeld no place for repentance to ſuch delinquents grounding their aſſertion vpon the 6. of the <hi>Hebr.</hi> and the fourth verſe. It is impoſſible that they which were once enlightned if they fall away ſhould bee renewed by repentance, whoſe eyes (ſay they) were twice o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, whom did our Sauiour rayſe the ſecond time from death to life, not <hi>Lazarus</hi> whom hee loued, nor the widowes ſonne whom hee pity<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Howſoeuer their poſition be he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall, that place being ment not of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15607:20"/> falling ſimply into ſinne, but of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling away from God by a generall and finall apoſtacie as ſome of the Iewes had done, who after they had giuen vp their names to Chriſt, to fight vnder his banner revolted to Iudaiſme, renou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cing that part which they might haue had in Chriſt the ſonne of <hi>Dauid:</hi> Yet ſurely this of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten relapſe into ſin is exceeding dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous,<note place="margin">Vulnus ite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratum ſanae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus tarduis. Auguſt.</note> if we argue by way of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon with thoſe diſeaſes of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, they do for the moſt part in ſhort time depriue it of life it ſelfe, becauſe by the often aſſaults of the ſame di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes nature is tyred, and exhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, his ſtrength wholy ſpent, and therefore ſhee is forced to yeeld vp her hold as not able to hold out any longer againe their violent invaſion vpon her:<note place="margin">Gutta cauat lapidem non viſed ſepe cadendo.</note> So fares it with the ſoule through the manifolde batteries of the ſame ſinnes, the life of grace may be quite extinquiſhed, what was the end of that man whoſe vncleane ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15607:20"/> beeing gone out returned againe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the laſt of that man was worſe then the beginning: Such was the caſe of <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtate after he had reuolted to paganiſme then the Deuill made him his owne,<note place="margin">Nazian. <hi>calles him</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Orat. contra Iul. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> then hee plunged him in all thoſe diabolicall arts which thoſe inſtruments of Satan <hi>Porphyrie</hi> &amp; his aſſociates taught him, then he playes the part of a ſauage beaſt againſt the poore Chriſtians, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ioyned with the deuil againſt God and his Chriſt, dying with that blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous ſcoffe in his mouth <hi>Viciſti Galilaee.</hi> So we reade in the life of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian</hi> the Atheiſt after his Apoſtacie from the Chriſtian profeſſion, he falls blaſphemouſly vpon Chriſt, cals him <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Luciau in Peregrino.</note> floutes and ſcoffes at all religion, &amp; is angry with himſelfe for being ſo vnaduiſed as to take that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion vpon him which got him no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but an elongation of his name from <hi>Lucius</hi> to <hi>Lucianus.</hi> This ſinne therefore of backſliding, of returning
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15607:21"/> with the dogge to the vomit, and the ſwine to her wallowing in the mire of ſin, by how much it exceeds in great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe by ſo much it deſerues a greater puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, almighty God as that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then <hi>Plato</hi> could note,<note place="margin">Plato in Timaeus.</note> it does <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> alwayes play the Geomitrician, not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiding by lot or by chance, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portioning his puniſhment to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of ſinnes. He that is angry with his brother vnaduiſedly is culpable of iudgement,<note place="margin">Math. 5.22</note> Hee that calles him Raca, (which <hi>Theophylact</hi> tranſlates <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) ſhall be puniſhed by the councell,<note place="margin">Quiea impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us eſt in rel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig. Th. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus.</note> but he that cals him foole ſhal be puniſhed with hell fyer. So in the prophet <hi>Amos</hi> for three tranſgreſſions and for foure, thats for ſeuen,<note place="margin">Amos 2.4.</note> a finite for an infinite, God will ſhew no fauour, He will not turn vnto Iudah, but will ſend out ſuch a fyer as ſhall deuoure the pallaces of Ieruſalem.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Leuit. 16.18.21.24. verſes.</note> And in <hi>Hoſea</hi> 5. from the 10. ver. almighty God follows the purſuit of ſinning, by a gradation of puniſhing Iudah was like them that remoued the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15607:21"/> bounds, that is, ſubuerted all order of true religion, Ephraim walked after the commandement, to wit, of <hi>Ierobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> which made Iſrael to ſinne, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will I be to Ephraim as a moath, and to the houſe of Iudah as rottennes verſe 12. the moath frets by degrees inſenſibly, but rottennes ruins at once ſuddenly, further <hi>Ephraim</hi> ſaw his ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and <hi>Iudah</hi> his wound, then went <hi>Ephraim</hi> vnto <hi>Aſhur</hi> and ſent vnto king <hi>Iareb,</hi> forſaking God and making fleſh their arme, reſting themſelues vpon the brittle reede of mans ſtrength, therfore will I be to <hi>Ephraim</hi> as a Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to the houſe of <hi>Iudah</hi> as a Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons whelpe, the Lyon is fierce and cruell but the Lyons whelpe is more bold (ſaies <hi>Plinie</hi>) for want of experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and more rauenous as being but newly blouded in the naturall courſe of deuouring. This for temporall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. As for eternall, S. <hi>Aug.</hi> tels vs, <hi>Si impius peccat in ſuo aeterno,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Impij amhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant in cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuitu.</note> 
               <hi>Deus puniet in ſuo aeterno,</hi> if wretched man
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15607:22"/> make no end in ſinning (walking in a circle of ſinne as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeakes of the wicked (with his <hi>amplius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 11.9.</note> yet a little more ſleepe, at leaſt a little ſlumber in ſinne, God for iuſtice ſake muſt make no end of puniſhing with his <hi>deterius,</hi> worſer and worſer, making thoſe tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall plagues but as a <hi>praeludium</hi> to thoſe aeternall ones, where the worme of conſcience neuer dyeth and the fire of Gods vengeance is vnquenchable, Therefore if thou beeſt <hi>made whole ſin no more, leaſt a worſe thing happen vnto thee.</hi> Out of all which praemiſes let vs deduce theſe briefe concluſions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the commemoration of the benefit receiued, It teaches that <hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficium excitat officium,</hi> Gods bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe ought to ſtirre vp our thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe. For as in euery donation there is a Giuer &amp; a Receiuer, ſo there ought to be a thankſgiuer, otherwiſe the knot of the three Graces is vnlooſed and vertue is diſhonoured. What if wee compare our condition to the caſe of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15607:22"/> this diſeaſed man, we were bruiſed and wounded by that ſubtle Serpent, who ſupplanted the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> and behold wee are made whole by the pretious balme of the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, <hi>He was broken for our ſinnes and by his ſtripes wee are healed:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 53.</note> What remaines but that we ſhould apply this note of remembrance to our ſelues, and ſo be ſtirred vp to offer alwaies to God the ſacrifice of praiſe and thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing for our happie deliuerance, and ſo much the more, becauſe it is more thankſ-worthy that Chriſt hath healed our diſeaſed ſoules, <hi>quam quod ſanarit languores corporum moriturorum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. in Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</note> then if He had reſtored our mortall bodies to perfect health. Ingratitude being ſo odious a vice, as the Heathen Orator,<note place="margin">Cicero.</note> ſaid all other vices were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehended in that one, as Irreligion towards the Gods, diſobedience towards our pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, neglect of the welfare of our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trey,<note place="margin">Ethic. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> which cauſed the ancient Graeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſaies <hi>Ariſt.</hi> to place the temple of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15607:23"/> Thankes in the middeſt of the ſtreete <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that being obvious to theeie it might alwaies put men in minde of remuneration: This temple was pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced euen in the midſt of <hi>Dauids</hi> heart, who pondering with himſelfe the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite mercies and benefits He had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued at Gods hands, breakes forth with <hi>A Quid retribuam?</hi> What ſhall I render vnto God for all the benefits, &amp;c? and reſolues the queſtion with this <hi>Accipiam calicem,</hi> I will take the cup of ſaluation and giue thanks: And with good reaſon, for euen the ſence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe creatures may teach man his leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,<note place="margin">Eccles. 1.2.</note> All the riuers goe into the Sea (ſayes <hi>Eccleſiaſt.</hi>) ſhewing themſelues tributaries to that place from whence they haue their originall: So euery good gift temporall; ſpirituall, eternall, flowing vnto man from the Ocean of Gods goodneſſe, man is bound by the law of retaliation to returne vnto him with all poſsible thankes for the ſame.</p>
            <p n="2">2. From the Commonition, <hi>Sinne
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15607:23"/> no more:</hi> the concluſion is, That ſinne is the cauſe of all affliction and diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the body. The ancient Heathen dreamed that many maladies were of a diuine nature, and from thence had power to ſubdue the ſtrength and courage of the ſtrongeſt body, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Plinie</hi> notes it that the Romans dedicated a Temple to the Goddeſſe Feuer to the end,<note place="margin">Plin. Nati-Chriſt. lib. <hi>2. Such were called</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Dij averun. cantes.</note> that whereas her Deitie could doe them ſmall good, yet that ſhee would bee ſo good as to doe them no hurt. Others aſcribed them to conſtellation of Planets, and to the apparition of Comets—<hi>Nocte comaetae.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>—Sanguinei lugubre rubent, aut Syrius ardor.</l>
               <l>Ille ſitim morboſque fereus mortalibus aegris.<note place="margin">Virgil.</note>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>Blaſphemous <hi>Porphyrie</hi> referred the contagion of the citie to the profeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſtian religion, becauſe after that had once gotten head Aeſculapius the God of health was neglected.<note place="margin">Ex Moru. de Rellig. Heſiod. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> The Greeke Poet—<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. they walke broad of their owne accord vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controlled,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15607:24"/> but the Philoſopher more truly yet after his naturall manner that diſeaſes are not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Ex Caelio Rhodig.</note> after the deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate councel of nature: becauſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is not a ſtep-mother ſeeking to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy her children, <hi>Sed</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by a certaine conſequence which the Phyſitian teaches to ariſe from the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportion of the foure Primarie qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities Hotte,<note place="margin">Ariſtotle de morte &amp; vitae.</note> Colde, Moiſt, Dry, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially heate and moyſture, when any of theſe vſurpe a tyranny ouer the reſt, the whole fabricke of this little world our body is put out of frame by the rebellious humours, ſtriuing to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-maſter one another. But the ſacred word of God conducts vs to the head and fountaine from whence all our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes haue their iſſue, and that's from the ſinne of our ſoule;<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note> for this cauſe many are ſicke and weake amongſt vs. Sinne, a thing ſo contagious <hi>vt vi, &amp; exuperantia ſua corpus quoque inficiat;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſ. in <hi>Cor. 11.</hi>
               </note> it flowes with ſuch a ſourſe as it ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowes the whole veſſell, who if He
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15607:24"/> had not ſinned, he had neuer been ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the arreſt of any diſeaſe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer:<note place="margin">Biel in ſent. Lumbard.</note> For whereas the Schoolemen obſerue but three ordinarie waies open to his deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, either the violence of man, crueltie of beaſts; defect in nature, againſt the 1. vniuerſal iuſtice ſhould ſo haue preuayled with men, that neither offence ſhould haue beene giuen, nor defence required. Againe, the ſecond the fierceſt of beaſts ſhould haue been in ſuch ſubiection to man that the litle child might haue plaied on the hole of the Baſilik without hurt:<note place="margin">Eſa. 11.8.</note>
               <note place="margin">Bonad. Arnob. lib. <hi>6. cals mans body</hi> domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilium mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borum. Horat.</note> and againſt the third he ſhould haue had <hi>optimum qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litatum temperamentum perfectae ſanita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> Such an equal temperature of theſe prime qualities as one ſhould neuer haue bin praedominate ouer the other, the humour radicall being maintained by the tree of life: But by his diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience forfeiting this large charter of his immunities to his ſoueraign Lord, <hi>Tunc noua febrìum, Terris incubuit co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hors,</hi> a whole army of maladies ſeazed
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15607:25"/> one mans body tugging &amp; hailing him to his long home, the Palſie ſhakes him the crampe pinches him, the megrime poſſeſſes the head, the ſquina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy ſeazes the throate, the feuer hectique appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends the whole body,<note place="margin">Eccl. 12.</note> vntill the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of his houſe begin to tremble, and the ſtrong men bow themſelues, the grinders ceaſe, and they that looke out at the windowes wax dimme, and the golden ewer and pitcher is broken, and then duſt returns to duſt, and the ſpirit to God that gaue it; The beſt elixor that we can extract out of this miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble condition,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.12.</note> is, that whereas ſinne is the mother of all ſorrow, yea of death it ſelfe: we ſhould for Chriſts ſake ſet the daughter againſt the mother, by ſorrowing a goodly ſorrow vnto true repentance, ſo may we haply preuent that tribulation and anguiſh that hangs ouer euery ſoule that ſinneth, at leaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe make death become no death vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, but a happy paſſage to a more happy life.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:15607:25"/>3. From the Commination, <hi>Leaſt a worſe thing happen vnto thee.</hi> The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion is, That multiplication of ſinne does neceſſarily inferre multiplication of miſery, and that in regard of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment both Temporall and Eternall. For the firſt the Heathen ſaid it,<note place="margin">Ariſt. Eth.</note> 
               <hi>Qui alium ebrius percuſſerit,</hi> and that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer beeing in his cups did ſtrike his fellow ſhould receiue double puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſe his ſin was doubled:<note place="margin">Gen. 18.25.</note> ſhal man be thus iuſt, and ſhal not the iudge of all the world doe right? yea ſurely, the ſentence is already gone out of Gods owne mouth, Reward her dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble according to her works,<note place="margin">Reu. 18.6.</note> and as much as ſhe hath glorified her ſelfe &amp; liued in pleaſure, ſo much giue yea to her ſorrow and torment. And S. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> renders a reaſon on Gods be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe why he ſhould thus proſecute re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge vpon refractary ſinners,<note place="margin">Chryſoſtom in locum. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ariſtotle.</note> 
               <hi>Si gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uem priorum ſceleru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paenam dederimus, &amp;c.</hi> If we haue beene formerly chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced for our faults and no whit bette<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:15607:26"/> wee prepare for our ſelues the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerer puniſhment becauſe wee ſeeme either Stupidi ſenceleſſe ſtocks more dull then the Aſſe who wil hearken to the admonition of the whippe though he be the dulleſt creature: Or elſe <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptores,</hi> contemners of the chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lord, ſpurning at Gods puniſhments as obdurate <hi>Pharao</hi> did, who though admoniſhed by many plagues, as ſo many ſummons to call him to repentance, yet would not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and let Iſrael goe, and therefore as he multiplied his ſinne of obſtinacy, ſo God meaſured out his puniſhment with greater ſeuerity. Secondly, for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall,<note place="margin">Math. 16.17 2. Cor. 3.10</note> when Chriſt the righteous iudge ſhal come in the glory of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then ſhall hee giue to euery man according to his deedes, not onely <hi>in quali,</hi> euill for euill, <hi>malu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paenae</hi> for <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum culpae, ſed in quanto,</hi> the greater euil of puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for the greater euil of ſin. As it was a paradox with the Stoicks to hold <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that all ſinnes are
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15607:26"/> equall, ſo is it as great a paradox with vs to hold that the helliſh puniſhment admits no difference, or degrees, <hi>Vnus ignis</hi> (ſaies S. <hi>Gregory</hi>) <hi>omnes concludet, ſed non aequaliter omnes comburet,</hi> One fire ſhal encompaſſe the damned crue, but ſhall not worke vpon all alike, It ſhall bee eaſier for Tyre and Sydon then for <hi>Corazin</hi> and <hi>Bethſaida,</hi> yet all fowre ſhall meete in one place, Hell. The ſeruant that knowes not his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters will, &amp;c. ſhall be beaten with few ſtripes, but he that knowes it and does it not ſhall ſuffer many: if thoſe barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous nations ſhall one day wring their hands and weep &amp; waile becauſe they haue knowne ſo little, and practiſed leſſe: much more ſhall we Chriſtians for knowing much, to little practiſe. All which may giue aduertiſement to two ſorts of ſinners, <hi>Deſperat ille vt peccet: Sperat iſte vt peccit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. in Pſal. <hi>144.</hi>
               </note> The firſt would ſeeme to deſpaire of ſaluation and makes that an encitement to him to take a full draught of the pleaſures of this life, becauſe they continue but
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:15607:27"/> for a ſeaſon. The ſecond ruſhes vpon all manner of ſinne, preſumption of pardon though he drinke vp iniquity like waters, and deuoures ſinne with greedines. S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> concludes, <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trumque metuendum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſ. 5.8.</note> the caſe of both of them is moſt fearefull, becauſe as they draw on iniquity with the cords of vanity and ſinne as with cartropes: ſo are they drawne ſayes <hi>Clemm. Alexan.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, like ſtaled oxen to the ſlaughter, with cords of their own making; treaſuring vp vnto themſelues wrath againſt the day of wrath: which is all one as if a man ſhould bee euery day gathering of ſticks and fewell to make the fire greater wherewith him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſhould be burned.</p>
            <p>Seeing thererefore we are by nature forgetful of Gods benefits, Seeing that all kinds of ſinne are to be auoided by vs, whether againſt the 1. or 2. table, whether ſmall or great, whether ſinnes of youth, age, complexion, conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, intenſion, either by a feruent deſire,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:15607:27"/> ſetled reluctation, or conſtant endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor, as the onely cauſe of all woe and miſery incident to the nature of man. Let vs alwaies be mindfull of God the giuer, to render due thanks for all his bleſſings, let vs ſo demeane our ſelues in all godly conuerſation, that though ſinne muſt dwell in our mortall bodies ſo long as we dwell in this earthly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, yet that it may not raigne in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the obeying it in the luſts ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: So may we preuent ſins attendants affliction of body, griefe, and anguiſh of ſoule, yea that laſt of al puniſhments eternall death. Which that wee may doe, Chriſt Ieſus our heauenly Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian who hath left vnto vs this whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome preſcript, <hi>of ſinning no more,</hi> grant vnto euery one of vs: To whom with the Father and Holy Ghoſt three Perſons in Vnity and one God in Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity be all prayſe, and power aſcribed now and for euer. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
